Division of Botany Archives
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
Division of Botany Archives
1864-2014
BOTAR.000001
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
7
1 map case; 4 boxes; 1 filing cabinet
The archives of the Division of Botany, icluding those of the Connecticut Botanical Society.
Division of Botany, Yale Peabody Museum
Biographical Sketch
The Yale University Herbarium was founded in 1864 and has as its nucleus the personal herbarium and library ofDaniel Cady Eaton. Originally under Yale University?s Department of Biology, the Herbarium?s administration was entrusted to the Peabody?s Division of Botany in 1968. In addition, it was the herbarium of record for the flora of Southern New England from 1864 until 1955, when that collection function passed to the University of Connecticut at Storrs.
For 31 years Eaton, whose special area of interest was ferns, curated the Herbarium. His 2-volume Ferns of North America, illustrated in color by Charles Faxon and J.H. Emerton, are housed in the Division of Botany.During his career Evans?s collection and research interests also turned to lichens. His lichen material was donated to the Smithsonian Insitution, but his bryophyte collection of approximately 35,000 specimens remains in the Yale Herbarium.
Eaton?s botanical interests were far ranging. He collected in Utah in the 1860s, and also contributed extensive floristic accounts to the United States Mexican Boundary Survey, Clarence King?s Geological Exploration of the 40th Parallel, George Wheeler?s Geographical Surveys West of the One Hundreth Meridian, and the Geological Survey of California. Many of these specimens remain in the Yale Herbarium.
Division holdings also include historic collections made in Scotland in 1808 by Sir William Hooker, and by his son Joseph Douglas Hooker during his 1848 travels to Sikkim. In addition, the Herbarium houses important collections made by James Dwight Dana during the Wilkes Expedition of 1838?1842, Frank Tweedy, Addison E. Verrill and by Eaton?s colleague William Henry Brewer. Brewer, Professor of Agriculture (1864?1903) at the Yale Sheffield Scientific School and Yale Professor of Foresty (1900?1903), collected throughout California in the years following the Gold Rush, and later on the Harriman Alaska Expedition of 1899.
One of Eaton?s last students, Alexander Williams Evans, devoted over 40 years to the taxonomy and geology of bryophytes as curator of the Herbarium collections and as Eaton Professor of Botany. Evans and his student Elwood Nichols, who later became Professor of Ecology, produced Bryophytes of Connecticut in 1908. John Reeder served as Curator of the Herbarium from 1947 to 1968. It was during Reeder?s tenure that the Herbarium?s emphasis shifted from ?lower? to ?higher? plants. Reeder?s work centered on the world?s true grasses. Along with his wife Charlotte, he expanded the Herbarium?s collection of Gramineae.
Donald Levin took over as Curator in 1969 and continued work on higher plants with studies of pollination ecology in Phlox, and of hybridization and genetic variability in plant populations. When Levin left Yale in 1973, James Rodman, a systematic botanist, became Curator-in-charge until his departure in 1983. For the next 17 years, the Division of Botany and the Yale Herbarium were managed by Curators of Paleobotany Leo Hickey and Bruce Tiffney. Tiffney left in 1986, leaving Hickey as Curator-in-charge. In 2000 Michael J. Donoghue joined the Yale faculty as G. Evelyn Hutchinson Professor of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology and was appointed Curator of Botany. From 2002 to 2007, Nico Cellinese served as the first Collections Manager of the Peabody?s Division of Botany and the Yale Herbarium. In 2008, Patrick Sweeney was hired as the Collections Manager.
Description of the Material
The archives of the Division of Botany notably include, correspondence, ledgers, maps and historical loan records.
Connecticut; North America; Maps; Correspondence; Prints; Paintings; Yale Peabody Museum; Yale University
- Connecticut Botanical Society, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Archives of the Connecticut Botanical Soicety.
  - Connecticut Maps. Connecticut quadrangle maps. n=115., 000004
- Correspondence, Series II
  Correspondence of the Division of Botany.
  - Correspondence., 1955-1976; 000030
  - Correspondence., 1977-1982; 000029
  - Correspondence., 1983; 000028
  - Correspondence., 1984; 000027
  - Correspondence., 1985; 000026
  - Correspondence., 1986; 000025
  - Correspondence., 1987; 000024
  - Correspondence., 1988; 000023
  - Correspondence., 1989; 000022
  - Correspondence., 1990; 000021
  - Correspondence., 1991-1992; 000019
  - Correspondence., 1991; 000020
  - Correspondence., 1992-1993; 000018
  - Correspondence., 1993-1996; 000016
  - Correspondence., 1994-1998; 000017
  - Correspondence., 1999; 000015
  - Job Related Correspondence., 000031
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence., 000043
  - Research Requests., 1996-1998; 000042
  - Research Requests., 1997-1999; 000041
  - Research Requests., 1998-1999; 000039
  - Research Requests., 1999-2000; 000040
- Maps, Series III
  Maps of the Division of Botany.
  - Connecticut Maps. Maps of the Yale Preserve and Yale Forest., 000006
  - Connecticut Maps. Historical topographic and geologic quadrangle maps., 000008
  - Distribution Maps. Distribution maps of various pines in North America., 000007
  - Miscellaneous. Miscellaneous tourist, topographic, etc. maps., 000010
  - Yale Plant Survey. Survey of plants on Yale Campus., 000009
- Prints, Plates and Figures, Series IV
  Various prints, plates, etc of the Division of Botany.
  - Plates and Prints. Two original ink drawings of algae (Sargassum?): one on acetate and the second on card stock. Each is provided with the label: "Dutch East Indies. Cpl. Shields. March 28, 1945 1/2 size". The drawing on acetate is marked as "plant 1"., 000311
  - Prints and Plates. Plates of Rhododendron, Trillium, Pteris, etc. Some colored., 000012
  - Prints and Plates. Pencil sketch of Aster anamolus and a print of Victoria sp., 000013
  - Prints and Plates. 4 prints of Victoria sp., 000014
- Miscellaneous, Series V
  - Amos Eaton's First Herbarium. Amos Eaton's First Herbarium in four volumes., 1815-1816; 000317
    - Amos Eaton's First Herbarium, volume 1. Amos Eaton's First Herbarium, volume 1., 1815-1816; 000319
    - Amos Eaton's First Herbarium, volume 2. Amos Eaton's First Herbarium, volume 2., 1815-1816; 000320
    - Amos Eaton's First Herbarium, volume 3. Amos Eaton's First Herbarium, volume 3., 1815-1816; 000321
    - Amos Eaton's First Herbarium, volume 4. Amos Eaton's First Herbarium, volume 4., 1815-1816; 000322
  - Amos Eaton's Second Herbarium. Amos Eaton's Second Herbarium, one volume. The Second Herbarium is thought to have comprised 2 books, however only one still exists. Larger than the others, it contains about 225 specimens. The front of the book has a specimen list in Amos Eaton?s handwriting; the specimen labels were handwritten by John Wright, Eaton?s student and co-author of the last edition of the Manual of Botany, published in 1840, 2 years before Eaton?s death. No type material has been found in the Second Herbarium.This volume represents one of the earliest plant collections in the United States, and remain of high historical importance., 18XX - 1834; 000318
  - Budget., 1976-1982; 000036
  - Budget., 1987-1991; 000035
  - Budget., 1991-1994; 000034
  - Budget. Miscellaneous budget information., 000049
  - CBS Grant., 000059
  - ESC Move., 000058
  - Employment Information., 000050
  - Job Descriptions., 000037
  - Microfiche. Copies of Famous Herbaria, advertisements., 000276
  - Miscellaneous Accession Information., 000053
  - Miscellaneous Grant Information., 000060
  - Miscellaneous., 000277
  - Myrdene Anderson Correspondence and Notes. Correspondence and Notes related to Plants of Northen Fennoscandia., 000032
  - Pest Management Information., 000054
  - Plants of Horse Island. L. Brown, Plants of Horse Island., 000286
  - Plants of Pakistan. C.E. Badgley, Plants of Pakistan., 000285
  - Publicity., 000056
  - Security., 000055
  - Space Planning., 000057
  - Specimens Available for Trade., 000284
  - Student Employment., 000051
  - The Horatio N. Fenn Collection, associated materials. Archives related to the aquisition and curation of the Horatio Nelson Fenn collection at Yale. 3 folders., 1980; 000312
  - The Horatio N. Fenn Collection. The Horatio Fenn Collection in four volumes. This material represents the earliest known collection of flora from Connecticut, over 1,000 botanical specimens collected and assembled in the New Haven area in 1822 by Horatio Nelson Fenn, then a student at the Yale Medical College., 000048
    - H.N. Fenn Collection, volume 1. Volume 1., 1822; 000313
    - H.N. Fenn Collection, volume 2. Volume 2., 1822; 000314
    - H.N. Fenn Collection, volume 3. Volume 3., 1822; 000315
    - H.N. Fenn Collection, volume 4. Volume 4., 1822; 000316
  - Volunteers., 1999-2000; 000052
  - Yale Herbarium Report. Report on the space occupied by the Yale University Herbarium in the Osborn Memorial Laboratories., 1980; 000038
- Ledgers, Specimen Lists, Card Files, etc., Series VI
  Ledgers, Specimen Lists, Card Files, etc.of the Division of Botany.
  - A-H Inventory., 000068
  - Arum., 000088
  - Asclepidaceae., 000071
  - Berberis., 000072
  - Boraginaceae., 000073
  - Cabinet I-Q., 000079
  - Cabinet Inventory. Count for Genus folders., 1994; 000063
  - Cabinet Q-3., 000078
  - Cabinet Q-5., 000076
  - Cabinet Q-6., 000075
  - Collections List. Collections List, 1970-Present., 000045
  - Collections List. Collections List, pre-1970., 000046
  - Compositae Inventory. 280, #66., 000070
  - Conifers., 000085
  - Databased Plants., 1995; 000090
  - Deaccessioned Specimens., 000047
  - Ferns., 000091
  - Fungi., 000069
  - Genus Folder Inventory 1-19. Families A-Q, 1-19., 000066
  - Genus Folder Inventory 19-194. Families 19-194., 000064
  - Genus Folder Inventory 19-81 (Originals)., 000067
  - Genus Folder Inventory 195-280. Families 195-280., 000065
  - Genus-Species Inventory., 1992; 000062
  - Gray Herbarium Index., 000061
  - Hepatica., 000080
  - Hepatica. Cabinet 2., 000092
  - Inventory by Country., 000089
  - Labels for Betula. Copies of labels for Betula, 1300-2391., 000303
  - Lichen., 000083
  - Liverworts., 000087
  - Marine Algae., 000084
  - Miscellaneous., 000093
  - Pinaceaa., 000086
  - Polypodiaceae. Cabinet 7., 000074
  - Polypodiaceae. Cabinet Q-4., 000077
  - Psilotum-Lycopodium., 000082
  - Selaginaceae., 000081
- Historical Loan Records, Series VII
  Loan records of the Division of Botany, not databased.
  - Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia., 000216
  - Accessions., 000274
  - Alan A. Beetle., 000104
  - Albert W. Herre., 000155
  - Albion College., 000098
  - Arizona State University., 000101
  - Arnold Arboretum., 000096
  - Bartley Herbarium of Ohio University., 000107
  - Bishop Museum., 000108
  - Bogor, Indonesia., 000111
  - Boston State College., 000112
  - Botany Institute, Academy of Sciences, USSR., 000174
  - British Museum., 000110
  - Brooklyn Botanic Garden., 000109
  - Bucknell University., 000114
  - Buenos Aires Museum., 000103
  - California Academy of Sciences., 000118
  - California Polytechnic State University, San Luis Obispo., 000208
  - California State Polytechnic University., 000131
  - Canada Agriculture Department., 000117
  - Canadian Department of Agriculture., 000134
  - Carnegie Museum., 000125
  - Catholic University of America., 000173
  - Central Michigan University., 000127
  - Charles University, Praha, Czechoslovakia., 000218
  - Children's Museum of Hartford., 000154
  - Chrysler Herbarium, Rutgers University., 000122
  - Clark University., 000132
  - Clinton, Mississippi College., 000124
  - Colorado State University., 000130
  - Connecticut Botanical Society., 000119
  - Copenhagen., 000115
  - Czechoslavian Academy of Sciences., 000133
  - D.H. Van Der Sluijs., 000233
  - Darlington Herbarium, West Chester University., 000141
  - Delaware State College., 000135
  - Depauw University., 000137
  - Dresden - Staatliches Museum fur Mineralogie und Geologie zu Dresden., 000138
  - Dudley Herbarium, Stanford University., 000139
  - Duke University., 000140
  - East China Normal University., 000158
  - Eastern Illinois University., 000142
  - Escuele Nacional de Cienceas., 000143
  - Exchanges., 000272
  - Faculte des Sciences Saint Jerome., 000180
  - Field Museum of Natural History., 000121
  - Florida Agricultural Experiment Station., 000145
  - Florida State University., 000147
  - Frankfurt., 000146
  - Fukuoka, Japan., 000149
  - Geneve, Jardin Botanique., 000148
  - Gifts made to Yale., 000273
  - Gray Herbarium., 000151
  - Great Falls College., 000152
  - H.K. Svenson., 000238
  - Hattori Botanical Laboratory., 000200
  - Helsinki., 000157
  - Huntington Botanical Gardens., 000156
  - Indiana University., 000164
  - Institute Agronomico do Norte Brazil., 000161
  - Institute of Botany, Portugal., 000176
  - Instituto de Pesquisas Jardim Botanico do Rio de Janeiro., 000223
  - Intermountain Herbarium, Utaha., 000257
  - International Rice Research Institute, Manila, Philippines., 000165
  - Jena, Germany., 000166
  - Kansas State University., 000172
  - Kew, Royal Botanical Gardens., 000168
  - L.H. Bailey Hortorium., 000106
  - Laval University, Quebec., 000222
  - Leersum, Netherlands., 000225
  - Liden - Rijksherbarium., 000170
  - Loans Within Yale., 000275
  - Marion College, Indiana., 000178
  - Marseille, France., 000179
  - Miami University., 000188
  - Michigan State University., 000187
  - Milwaukee Public Museum., 000184
  - Missouri Botanical Garden., 000186
  - Montana State University., 000189
  - Museum National d'Histore Naturelle., 000220
  - Museum National d'Historie Naturelle., 000215
  - National Herbarium, Caracas, Venezuela., 000259
  - National Herbarium, New South Wales., 000204
  - National Herbarium, Pretoria South Africa., 000219
  - National Museum of Canada., 000116
  - National Park Service., 000190
  - National Science Museum, Tokyo., 000246
  - Nature Conservancy., 000194
  - Naturhistoriska Riksmuseum., 000230
  - Naturhistoriska Riksmuseum., 000235
  - New Brunswick Museum., 000193
  - New York Botanical Garden., 000206
  - New York State Museum., 000207
  - Norges Teknisk-Naturvitenskapelige. Norway., 000205
  - North Adams State College., 000192
  - North Coast Herbarium, Sonoma State University., 000195
  - Northeast Louisiana University., 000201
  - Northern Kentucky University., 000171
  - Norwich University., 000202
  - Notre Dame University., 000197
  - Ohio State University., 000211
  - Old Dominion University., 000212
  - Oregon State University., 000214
  - Overdue Loans., 000095
  - Pedro S. Coronado., 000129
  - Philippine National Herbarium., 000217
  - Purdue University., 000221
  - Rancho Santa Ana Herbarium., 000229
  - Research Institue of Botany of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences., 000159
  - Rocky Mountain Herbarium., 000227
  - Southern Connecticut State College., 000231
  - Southern Illinois University., 000232
  - Southern Methodist University., 000234
  - Texas A&M., 000239
  - Texas Research Foundation., 000177
  - Trinity College, Hartford., 000243
  - United States Department of Agriculture., 000254
  - United States National Arboretum., 000191
  - United States National Herbarium., 000255
  - Universitat Bern., 000105
  - Universite de Liege., 000175
  - University of Alaska., 000097
  - University of Alberta., 000099
  - University of Arizona., 000100
  - University of Auborn., 000102
  - University of Bridgeport., 000113
  - University of British Columbia., 000248
  - University of California, Santa Barbara., 000250
  - University of California., 000249
  - University of Cincinnati., 000123
  - University of Connecticut, Stamford., 000126
  - University of Connecticut., 000128
  - University of Delhi., 000136
  - University of Georgia., 000150
  - University of Gottingen., 000153
  - University of Idaho., 000162
  - University of Illinois., 000163
  - University of Iowa., 000160
  - University of Kansas., 000167
  - University of Malaya., 000169
  - University of Massachusetts., 000181
  - University of Mexico., 000182
  - University of Michigan., 000183
  - University of Minnesota., 000185
  - University of Nebraska., 000198
  - University of Nebraska., 000203
  - University of Nevada., 000224
  - University of New Hampshire., 000199
  - University of New Mexico., 000252
  - University of North Carolina., 000196
  - University of North Carolina., 000253
  - University of Oklahoma., 000210
  - University of Oregon., 000213
  - University of Oxford., 000144
  - University of Reading., 000228
  - University of Rhode Island., 000226
  - University of Science and Arts of Oklahoma., 000209
  - University of Stockholm., 000236
  - University of Tennessee., 000240
  - University of Texas., 000241
  - University of Tokyo., 000242
  - University of Toronto., 000244
  - University of Turka, Finland., 000245
  - University of Ulm., 000251
  - University of Utah., 000256
  - University of Vermont., 000262
  - University of Washington., 000267
  - University of Western Ontario., 000258
  - University of Wichita., 000264
  - University of Wisconsin., 000265
  - University of the South Pacific., 000237
  - Utrecht., 000247
  - Vanderbilt University., 000261
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute., 000260
  - Virginius H. Chase., 000120
  - Wartburg College., 000263
  - Washington State University., 000266
  - West Virginia University., 000268
  - Yale University, Requests for Loans., 000271
  - Yale University, School of Forestry., 000270
  - Yale University., 000269
- Divisional History, Series VIII
  Archives related to historical information on the Division of Botany.
  - Biographies., 000283
  - Divisional History. Reprints, articles and personal communications related to the history of the division., 000279
  - Divisional History. Organization of the General Collection., 000280
  - Divisional History. Reprints, articles and personal communications related to the history of the division., 000282
  - George E. Nichols. G.E. Nichols Ecology lecture notes., 1937; 000281
  - Visitor Logs., 000302
- Collections, Series IX
  Archives related to specific collections.
  - A. Fendler, Ferns of Trinidad., 000291
  - A.W. Evans Cladonia., 000290
  - Amos Eaton Book Collection., 000288
  - Amos Eaton Herbarium. Notes, article on the A. Eaton Herbarium., 000289
  - Annette Harkis Collection. Index of the Annette Harkins Collection., 000310
  - Anton N.J. Heyn Collection. Correspondence, lists, etc. of the Heyn Collection., 000293
  - Charles L. Remington Collection. Charles Remington collection archives., 000294
  - Donald MacVicar Collection. Archives relating to the D. MacVicar Collection., 000299
  - Ethanol Collection. Inventory of the Ethanol Collection., 000301
  - Frank Tweedy Collection. Archives relating to the F. Tweedy Collection., 000297
  - Harold Conklin Collection. Correspondence, determinations and fieldbook data., 000287
  - Oran B. Stanley Yale Forest Collection. Archives relating to the O.B. Stanley Collection., 000300
  - Paul M. Taylor Collection. Correspondence, collecting data, etc. related to the P.M. Taylor Collection., 000296
  - Pierre Ventur Collection. Archives relating to the P. Ventur Collection., 000298
  - Rosemary Gianno, Resin Collection., 000292
- Field Notebooks, Series X
  - James A. Chu Field Notebook. Benthic Marine Algae of the Yale Biological Station, Guilford, CT., Jun 1971 - Aug 1971; 000305
  - Judy Stone Field Notebook., 1986; 000307
  - Mark Ashton Field Notebook., 1984; 000306
  - Martha Hill Field Notebook., 1984-1985; 000308
  - Miscellaneous Field Notebook., 000309